Intelligent, but none is born with the skill to use a tool
Youngsters like this one must learn by watching
She uses special tools one after another to get all the honey she can and in a few minutes
She destroys what took the bees years to build in the rain forest
Nothing is safe
Here in the Congo there can be as many as 500 trees crammed into every acre
In the battle for space some will rise to over 60 meters high in just a few decades
In a valley like this there could be close on 1,000 different species of tree
Up here the crowns barely touch each tree seems to respect its neighbors space
When they germinate down on the forest floor young trees and plants are less restrained
But every new generation fights it out in battles. We can see by accelerating time
They must get light if they are to survive
And they squeeze crush and even a slash one another in order to reach it
Despite the thick canopy above some sunlight does filter through and allows a few low-light
Specialists to bloom near the forest floor down here
There are animals too that seek out the sunlight the forest's largest predator a female rock python
Her body is five meters long weighs a hundred kilos and has
4,000 muscles that she uses to crush the life out of her victims
But right now her need is not for food. It's for warmth
she finds a rare patch where a shaft of sunlight strikes the ground and
She begins to bask
She's cold-blooded. So this is the only way she can raise the temperature of her body
But now she's becoming very warm indeed more than 10 degrees hotter than usual at 40 degrees centigrade
She's in danger of killing herself
Just in time she moves off. He disappears below ground
This is her nest and it's full of giant eggs
It's critical for the eggs development that they stay above 30 degrees
Here in this special filming burrow. She gently wraps her superheated body around the eggs
Passing on to them the warmth of the Sun
She has done this every day for three months
the repeated heat stress on her body is so great it could be lethal and
At the very least it will take three years for her to recover from incubating this one clutch of eggs
her parchment shelled eggs carry the pressed imprint of her scales an
Indication of the strength of her embrace
At last her efforts are rewarded
But the babies can't stay here. They must leave their sanctuary and find food in the tangled world above
They're over 60 centimeters long already big enough to be a threat to the smaller inhabitants of the forest
But they are themselves vulnerable